<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx>
   <body>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                1
            
            Thus the
                heavens and the earth were completed in all their vast array.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                1
            
            Ainsi
                furent achevés le ciel et la terre avec toute l'armée de ce
                qu'ils contiennent.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg/>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                2
            
            Le
                septième <hi x="4">jour</hi>, <hi x="1">Dieu</hi> avait achevé tout ce qu'il avait
                créé. Alors il se reposa
            
                2.2 
                Verbe d'où dérive le mot hébreu qui
                    désigne le sabbat.
            
             en ce
                <hi x="4">jour</hi>-là de toutes les œuvres qu'il avait accomplies.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                2
            
            By the
                seventh <hi x="4">day</hi> 
               <hi x="1">God</hi> had finished the work he had been doing; so on the seventh <hi x="4">day</hi> he
                rested from all his work. 
            
                3
            
            Then <hi x="1">God</hi>
                blessed the seventh <hi x="4">day</hi> and made it holy, because on it he rested from all the work
                of creating that he had done.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                3
            
            Il
                bénit le septième <hi x="4">jour</hi>, il en fit un <hi x="4">jour</hi> saint, car, en ce
                <hi x="4">jour</hi>-là, il se reposa de toute l'œuvre de création
                qu'il avait accomplie
            
                2.3 
                Allusion en Ex
                        20.11.
            
            .
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>Adam and Eve</seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>L'histoire des débuts de l'humanité</seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                4
            
            This is
                the account of the heavens and the earth when they were created, when the 
            
                
            
             <hi x="1">God</hi> made
                the earth and the heavens.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>L'alliance d'Eden</seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg/>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                4
            
            Voici
                l'histoire de ce qui est advenu au ciel et sur la terre lorsqu'ils
                furent créés.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                5
            
            Now no
                shrub had yet appeared on the earth
            
                2:5 
                Or 
                land
                ; also in verse 6
            
             and no
                plant had yet sprung up, for the 
            
                
            
             <hi x="1">God</hi> had
                not sent rain on the earth and there was no one to work the ground, 
            
                6
            
            but
                streams
            
                2:6 
                Or 
                mist
            
             came up
                from the earth and watered the whole surface of the ground. 
            
                7
            
            Then the 
            
                
            
             <hi x="1">God</hi>
                formed a man
            
                2:7 
                The Hebrew for 
                man 
                (adam) sounds like and may be related to
                    the Hebrew for 
                ground 
                (adamah); it is also the name 
                Adam 
                (see verse 20).
            
             from the
                dust of the ground and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life, and the man
                became a living being.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            Au temps
                où l'Eternel <hi x="1">Dieu</hi> fit la terre et le ciel, 
            
                5
            
            il
                n'existait encore sur la terre aucun arbuste, et aucune herbe des champs
                n'avait encore germé, car l'Eternel <hi x="1">Dieu</hi> n'avait pas fait
                pleuvoir sur la terre, et il n'y avait pas d'homme pour cultiver la
                terre. 
            
                6
            
            De
                l'eau se mit à sourdre et à irriguer toute la surface du
                sol.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                8
            
            Now the 
            
                
            
             <hi x="1">God</hi> had
                planted a garden in the east, in Eden; and there he put the man he had formed. 
            
                9
            
            The 
            
                
            
             <hi x="1">God</hi> made
                all kinds of trees grow out of the ground—trees that were pleasing to the eye
                and good for food. In the middle of the garden were the tree of life and the tree of
                the knowledge of good and evil.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                7
            
            L'Eternel <hi x="1">Dieu</hi> façonna l'homme avec de la poussière du
                sol, il lui insuffla dans les narines le souffle de vie, et l'homme devint un
                être vivant
            
                2.7 
                Allusion en 1 Co
                        15.45.
            
            .
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                10
            
            A river
                watering the garden flowed from Eden; from there it was separated into four
                headwaters. 
            
                11
            
            The name
                of the first is the Pishon; it winds through the entire land of Havilah, where there
                is gold. 
            
                12
            
            (The
                gold of that land is good; aromatic resin
            
                2:12 
                Or 
                good; pearls
            
             and
                onyx are also there.) 
            
                13
            
            The name
                of the second river is the Gihon; it winds through the entire land of Cush.
            
                2:13 
                Possibly southeast Mesopotamia
            
             
            
                14
            
            The name
                of the third river is the Tigris; it runs along the east side of Ashur. And the
                fourth river is the Euphrates.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                8
            
            L'Eternel <hi x="1">Dieu</hi> planta un jardin vers l'orient : l'Eden, le
                pays des Délices. Il y plaça l'homme qu'il avait
                façonné.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                15
            
            The 
            
                
            
             <hi x="1">God</hi>
                took the man and put him in the Garden of Eden to work it and take care of it. 
            
                16
            
            And the 
            
                
            
             <hi x="1">God</hi>
                commanded the man, —You are free to eat from any tree in the garden; 
            
                17
            
            but you
                must not eat from the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, for when you eat from
                it you will certainly die."
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                9
            
            L'Eternel <hi x="1">Dieu</hi> fit pousser du sol toutes sortes d'arbres portant des
                fruits d'aspect agréable et délicieux, et il mit l'arbre
                de la vie
            
                2.9 
                Voir Pr 3.18 ;
                            Ap 2.7 ; 22.2,14.
            
             au milieu
                du jardin. Il y plaça aussi l'arbre de la détermination du bien
                et du mal
            
                2.9 
                Autre traduction : 
                l'arbre de la connaissance du bien et du mal 
                (de même au v. 17).
            
            .
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                18
            
            The 
            
                
            
             <hi x="1">God</hi>
                said, “It is not good for the man to be alone. I will make a helper suitable
                for him."
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                10
            
            Du pays
                d'Eden sortait un fleuve qui arrosait le jardin. De là, il se divisait
                en quatre bras.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                19
            
            Now the 
            
                
            
             <hi x="1">God</hi> had
                formed out of the ground all the wild animals and all the birds in the sky. He
                brought them to the man to see what he would name them; and whatever the man called
                each living creature, that was its name. 
            
                20
            
            So the
                man gave names to all the livestock, the birds in the sky and all the wild
                animals.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                11
            
            Le nom
                du premier est Pishôn : il contourne tout le pays de Havila où se
                trouve de l'or, 
            
                12
            
            un or
                d'excellente qualité. On trouve aussi dans cette contrée de
                l'ambre parfumée et la pierre précieuse appelée
                onyx.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            But for
                Adam
            
                2:20 
                Or 
                the man
            
             no
                suitable helper was found. 
            
                21
            
            So the 
            
                
            
             <hi x="1">God</hi>
                caused the man to fall into a deep sleep; and while he was sleeping, he took one of
                the man’s ribs
            
                2:21 
                Or 
                took part of the man’s side
            
             and
                then closed up the place with flesh. 
            
                22
            
            Then the 
            
                
            
             <hi x="1">God</hi>
                made a woman from the rib
            
                2:22 
                Or 
                part
            
             he had
                taken out of the man, and he brought her to the man.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                13
            
            Le
                deuxième fleuve s'appelle Guihôn, il parcourt tout le pays de
                Koush
            
                2.13 
                Koush 
                désigne habituellement le Soudan ou l'Ethiopie. Le
                    fleuve serait donc le Nil. Certains situent cependant le pays de Koush, dont
                    parle ce passage, en Mésopotamie, à l'est du Tigre, et
                    l'identifient à la région du peuple des Kassites.
            
            .
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                23
            
            The man
                said,
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                14
            
            Le
                troisième fleuve s'appelle le Tigre, c'est celui qui coule
                à l'orient de l'Assyrie.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            “This is now bone of my bones
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            Et le
                quatrième fleuve c'est l'Euphrate.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            and
                flesh of my flesh;
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                15
            
            L'Eternel <hi x="1">Dieu</hi> prit l'homme et l'établit dans le jardin
                d'Eden pour le cultiver et le garder.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            she
                shall be called ‘woman,’
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                16
            
            Et
                l'Eternel <hi x="1">Dieu</hi> ordonna à l'homme : Mange librement des
                fruits de tous les arbres du jardin, 
            
                17
            
            sauf du
                fruit de l'arbre de la détermination du bien et du mal. De
                celui-là, n'en mange pas, car le <hi x="4">jour</hi> où tu en mangeras, tu
                mourras.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            for she
                was taken out of man."
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                18
            
            L'Eternel <hi x="1">Dieu</hi> dit : Il n'est pas bon que l'homme soit seul,
                je lui ferai une aide qui soit son vis-à-vis.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                24
            
            That is
                why a man leaves his father and mother and is united to his wife, and they become
                one flesh.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                19
            
            L'Eternel <hi x="1">Dieu</hi>, qui avait façonné du sol tous les animaux des
                champs et tous les oiseaux du ciel, les fit venir vers l'homme pour voir
                comment il les nommerait, afin que tout être vivant porte le nom que
                l'homme lui donnerait. 
            
                20
            
            L'homme donna donc un nom à tous les animaux domestiques, à
                tous les oiseaux du ciel et aux animaux sauvages. Mais il ne trouva pas d'aide
                qui soit son vis-à-vis.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
      <tu>
         <tuv xml:lang="en_GB">
            <seg>
            
                25
            
            Adam and
                his wife were both naked, and they felt no shame.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
         <tuv xml:lang="fr">
            <seg>
            
                21
            
            Alors
                l'Eternel <hi x="1">Dieu</hi> plongea l'homme dans un profond sommeil. Pendant que
                celui-ci dormait, il prit une de ses côtes
            
                2.21 
                Autre traduction : 
                une partie du côté de l'homme.
            
             et
                referma la chair à la place. 
            
                22
            
            L'Eternel <hi x="1">Dieu</hi> forma une femme de la côte qu'il avait prise de
                l'homme, et il l'amena à l'homme.
        </seg>
         </tuv>
      </tu>
   </body>
</tmx>
